<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>The Knowledge Agent</title>

  <para>The knowledge agent is a component which is embedded in knowledge-api.
  To use this, you don't need any extra components. In fact, if you are using
  Guvnor, your application should only need to include the knowledge-api and
  drools-core dependencies in its classpath (drools and mvel JARs only), and
  no other rules specific dependencies.</para>

  <para>Note that there is also a drools-ant ant task, so you can build rules
  as part of an Ant script (for example in cases where the rules are edited in
  the IDE) without using Guvnor at all - the drools-ant task will generate
  .pkg files the same as Guvnor.</para>

  <para>Once you have "built" your rules in a package in Guvnor (or from the
  ant task), you are ready to use the agent in your target application.</para>

  <para>The Following example constructs an agent that will build a new
  KnowledgeBase from the files specified in the path String. It will poll
  those files every 60 seconds, which is the default, to see if they are
  updated. If new files are found it will construct a new KnowledgeBase. If
  the change set specifies a resource that is a directory it's contents will
  be scanned for changes too.</para>

  <programlisting language="Java">KnowledgeAgent kagent = KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "MyAgent" );
kagent.applyChangeSet( ResourceFactory.newUrlResource( url ) );
KnowledgeBase kbase = kagent.getKnowledgeBase();</programlisting>

  <para>The KnowledgeAgent can accept a configuration that allows for some of
  the defaults to be changed. An example property is
  <code>drools.agent.scanDirectories</code>, by default any specified
  directories are scanned for new additions, it is possible to disable
  this.</para>

  <programlisting language="Java">KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
KnowledgeAgentConfiguration kaconf = KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgentConfiguration();

// we do not want to scan directories, just files
kaconf.setProperty( "drools.agent.scanDirectories", "false" ); 

// the name of the agent
KnowledgeAgent kagent = KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "test agent", kaconf );

// resource to the change-set xml for the resources to add                                                                  
kagent.applyChangeSet( ResourceFactory.newUrlResource( url ) ); </programlisting>

  <para>An example of the <filename>change-set.xml</filename> file.</para>

  <programlisting language="XML">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;change-set xmlns="http://drools.org/drools-5.0/change-set"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
            xs:schemaLocation="http://drools.org/drools-5.0/change-set http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/labs/labs/jbossrules/trunk/drools-api/src/main/resources/change-set-1.0.0.xsd" &gt;
    &lt;add&gt;
      &lt;resource source="&guvnor.url.base;/org.drools.guvnor.Guvnor/package/mortgages/LATEST" type="PKG" basicAuthentication="enabled" username="uid" password="pwd"/&gt;
    &lt;/add&gt; 
&lt;/change-set&gt;</programlisting>

  <important>
    <para>The User ID and Password in the change-set should be consistent with
    the requirements of the Authenticator configured in components.xml. By
    default, a NilAuthenticator is configured that does not authenticate HTTP
    requests and hence the "basicAuthentication", "username" and "password"
    attributes are not required. If you change components.xml to use another
    Authenticator you will need to ensure appropriate authentication
    credentials are set in the change-set. Please refer to the "Security -
    Authentication and basic access" section of the "Administration Guide" for
    more details.</para>
  </important>

  <note>
    <para>The change-set schema, change-set-1.0.0.xsd, is also included in the
    knowledge-api JAR file applicable to the version of Drools you are
    running.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Resource scanning is not on by default, it's a service and must be
  started, the same is for notification. This can be done via the
  ResourceFactory.</para>

  <programlisting language="Java">ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeNotifierService().start();
ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeScannerService().start();</programlisting>

  <para>Following shows the deployment screen of Guvnor, which provides URLs
  and downloads of packages.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Snapshot deployment</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/SnapshotDeploy.png"
                   format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>You can see the "Package URI" - this is the URL that you would copy
  and paste into the <filename>change-set.xml</filename> file to specify that
  you want this package. It specifies an exact version (in this case to a
  snapshot) - each snapshot has its own URL. If you want the latest snapshot,
  replace the name of the snapshot in the URL with the word "LATEST".</para>

  <para>You can also download a .pkg file from here, which you can drop in a
  directory and use the "file" or "dir" feature of the KnowledgeAgent if
  needed (in some cases people will not want to have the runtime automatically
  contact Guvnor for updates - but that is generally the easiest way for many
  people).</para>
</section>
