<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>WebDAV and HTTP</title>

  <para>The repository back end can also be accessed via webdav. WebDAV is a
  http based file system API - which has clients on all platforms (some
  operating systems such as windows can connect directly to WebDAV
  repositories almost like a file system.</para>

  <section>
    <title>WebDAV</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Windows webdav</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WebDAVWindows.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In windows the "web folders" feature can be used. On OSX - the free
    Cyberduck client can work well. To access the repository as webdav, you
    the url is the same as the web interface, only with /webdav at the end,
    instead of <filename>Guvnor.html</filename>. Authentication will be
    required to get access this way. This will show a packages and snapshots
    directory - the snapshots directory is read only (a view of created
    snapshots of packages). The packages directory will contain a list of
    packages in the repository, drilling in to them will show the individual
    assets as files.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>URLs</title>

    <para>There are a few other URLs which are handy to know exist. The
    package deployment URL mentioned in the section about knowledge agent
    deployment also has a few other features: By appending
    <filename>.drl</filename> to the end of a URL, you will show the generated
    DRL for that package. e.g.:
    <filename>/package/testPDSGetPackage/LATEST.drl</filename> - will show the
    DRL (not the binary package) for the latest package. Further to this, you
    can append <filename>/assetName.drl</filename> - and it will show the
    generated DRL for that item. (even if it isn't a DRL file). E.g.
    <filename>/package/testPDSGetPackage/LATEST/SomeFile.drl</filename>.</para>
  </section>
</section>
