<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"  xml:base="../..">
  <title>Categories</title>

  <figure>
    <title>Categories</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/CatZoom.png"
                   format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Categories allow rules (assets) to be labeled (or tagged) with any
  number of categories that you define. This means that you can then view a
  list of rules that match a specific category. Rules can belong to any number
  of categories. In the above diagram, you can see this can in effect create a
  folder/explorer like view of assets. The names can be anything you want, and
  are defined by the Guvnor administrator (you can also remove/add new
  categories - you can only remove them if they are not currently in
  use).</para>

  <para>Generally categories are created with meaningful name that match the
  area of the business the rule applies to (if the rule applies to multiple
  areas, multiple categories can be attached). Categories can also be used to
  "tag" rules as part of their life-cycle, for example to mark as "Draft" or
  "For Review".</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Assets can have multiple categories</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/CatEdit.png"
                   format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The view above shows the category editor/viewer that is seen when you
  open an asset. In this example you can see the asset belongs to 2
  categories, with a "+" button to add additional items (use the trash can
  item to remove them). This means that when either category is used to show a
  list of assets, you will see that asset.</para>

  <para>In the above example, the first Category "Finance" is a "top level"
  category. The second one: "HR/Awards/QAS" is a still a single category, but
  its a nested category: Categories are hierarchical. This means there is a
  category called "HR", which contains a category "Awards" (it will in fact
  have more sub-categories of course), and "Awards" has a sub-category of QAS.
  The screen shows this as "HR/Awards/QAS" - its very much like a folder
  structure you would have on your hard disk (the notable exception is of
  course that rules can appear in multiple places).</para>

  <para>When you open an asset to view or edit, it will show a list of
  categories that it currently belongs to If you make a change (remove or add
  a category) you will need to save the asset - this will create a new item in
  the version history. Changing the categories of a rule has no effect on its
  execution.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Creating categories</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/AdminCats.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The above view shows the administration screen for setting up
  categories (there) are no categories in the system by default. As the
  categories can be hierarchical you chose the "parent" category that you want
  to create a sub-category for. From here categories can also be removed (but
  only if they are not in use by any current versions of assets).</para>

  <para>As a general rule, an asset should only belong to 1 or 2 categories at
  a time. Categories are critical in cases where you have large numbers of
  rules. The hierarchies do not need to be too deep, but should be able to see
  how this can help you break down rules/assets into manageable chunks. Its ok
  if its not clear at first, you are free to change categories as you
  go.</para>
</section>
