<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Services</title>

  <para>
    Service Config is a special asset that defines an execution
    service configuration. This execution service is a war file (generated
    automatically by the editor) which you can deploy to execute KnowledgeBases
    remotely for any sort of client application. As this service is stateless,
    it is possible to have as many of these services deployed as you need to
    serve the client load.
  </para>

  <para>
    This version of the execution server supports as many Knowledge Bases
    as you need, supporting also multiple stateless and stateful sessions
    in a native way.
  </para>

  <para>
    To create a new Service you have to go to "Create New" -> "New Service Config"
    option in Knowledge Base section of Guvnor. In the following sections you have
    detailed information on how to configure your Service Config.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Service Configuration Editor</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig1.png"
                   format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring Multiple Knowledge Bases</title>
    <para>
      As already mentioned the Service editor allows users configure as
      many knowledge bases as they need. This section describes how to use the
      tabbed panel to configure your Service with multiple knowledge bases.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Tabbed Panel</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig2.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The above panel is composed by the following:
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Named Tab: each tab represents a knowledge base, and once selected,
            its configuration panel is displayed. See next section for further information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Removing: in order to remove an existing tab/knowledge base, you have to
            click the highlighted "X" and then confirm the action. Important to note that
            should exists at least one knowledge base.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add new: to add a new kbase, all you need is click on this special tab.
            The new kbase will be added on the left hand side of the plus tab.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Knowledge Base Configuration Panel</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Knowledge Base Configuration</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig3.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      In the above configuration panel you have 6 items that you can interact with:
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Add Asset Button: add new assets to the tree using a wizard.
            See next section for further information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove Selected Button: remove the selected assets (the ones
            that are checked) from Assets Tree.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Rename KBase Button: this button will open a standard “prompt
            for rename” dialog box.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Advanced Options Button: opens the advanced knowledge base
            configuration dialog. Configurations that are not available in the
            panel, should be available in this advanced dialog. Detailed information
            about it can be found in the "Advanced Knowledge Base Configuration Options"
            section.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assets Tree: Here you have the complete set of assets, grouped by
            package and type, that are referenced by the active knowledge base configuration.
            For additional information, please read the "Assets Tree" section.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sessions Grid: Here users can create, delete and edit in place a list of
            desires ksessions. For detailed instructions on how to configure ksessions,
            please check the "Configuring Knowledge Sessions" section.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Assets using Wizard</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding Assets resources</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig4.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        This Wizard has 3 sections:
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Package: Use this field to filter the assets of a particular
              Package. By default the selected package is the one that your
              Service belongs to, but you're not limited to it as you can
              select any other package that you want.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Format: Use this field to filter the type of assets you are
              looking for.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Assets: The list of assets that match the selected package and
              format. You can select one or more assets using the check-box column
              and then click "OK" to add each resource to the Assets Tree of your
              active knowledge base configuration.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Advanced Knowledge Base Configuration Options</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Advanced Options Dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig5.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        This dialog has the following sections:
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>MBeans: Can enable or disable MBeans on active knowledge base. Users can also
              keep the default engine behavior by choosing the Default option.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Event Processing Mode: Defines the event processing mode, which options are
              Cloud or Stream. Users can also keep the default engine behavior by choosing
              the Default option. For more information about Event Processing Mode,
              consult the Drools Fusion documentation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Assert Behavior: Defines the expected assert behavior, which options are
              Identity and Equality. Users can also keep the default engine behavior by
              choosing the Default option.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Assets Security Information: This section holds any security related
              configuration to remotely access the guvnor repository.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enable Authentication, User name and Password: If explicit authentication
              is enabled, you should provide the user name and password for remote access.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Assets Tree</title>
      <figure>
        <title>The Assets Tree</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig6.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The assets tree is composed by 4 different types of nodes:
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Knowledge Base: Root node that represents the active kbase.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Packages: Selected assets are grouped by its packages. Important to note that
              those packages are just informative and are not relevant for the service runtime.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Asset Types: Groups assets of the same package by type. The actual list of
              supported types are: brl, drl, dsl, bpmn2, gdst, changeset and jars.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Assets: Selected assets of a given type (parent) and package (grandparent).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Knowledge Sessions</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Knowledge Sessions Grid - basic information to define a ksession
          are available to be edited in place.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig7.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The ksessions grid is composed by the following columns:
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Add and Remove Icons: Users can use these icons to add new or remove existing
              knowledge sessions. Important to note that should exists at least one knowledge
              session.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Knowledge Session Name: Defines the ksession name. Users can edit this particular
              field in place as highlighted on box "A".
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Session Type: Defines if a ksession is Stateless or Stateful. Users can also select
              the desired type directly on the grid.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuration Button: This button opens the knowledge session configuration dialog.
              See next section for further information.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Knowledge Session Configuration Options</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Knowledge Session Configuration Dialog</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig8.png"
                         format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          This ksession configuration dialog has the following 5 fields:
          <orderedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>URL: Defines a custom URL to access the active ksession.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Protocol: Defines the protocol that ksession should be accessed by,
                default options is REST.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Marshalling: Defines which marshalling technology should be used,
                default option is XStream.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Clock Type: Defines the type of the session clock, which options are
                Pseudo or Real Time. Users can also keep the default engine behavior by
                choosing the Default option.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Keep Reference: Enable or disable the engine to keep a weak reference
                of this section on the kbase. Users can also use the default engine behavior
                by choosing the Default option.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>

      </section>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Downloading War &amp; Managing Dependencies</title>

    <para>After configuring your knowledge bases and sessions, you're ready to download
      the service war. For so, all you need to do is click on the "Download War" button and
      the following screen (or a similar one, depending on your browser) will show up.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>Downloading WAR</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig10.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <warning>
      <para>Before click on the "Download War" button, makes sure that you don't
        have pending changes. This is a very important step, once the the war file
        is generated based on the latest saved information and not on the current
        screen state.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
      The generated file is a ready to be deployed war file. Which mean that it contains all
      the necessary configuration files and all the needed dependencies as well. As dependency
      management is a crucial subject in a real world applications deployment, we will discuss
      that in more detail in the next section.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Dependency Management</title>

      <para>As already mentioned, the generated war file contains all the necessary dependencies
        to execute the configured Service, it works seamlessly on most standard containers.
      </para>

      <para>But the reality is a bit different, rarely you'll have a "standard container",
        usually what you have is an already configured and running container. Probably this
        container even have already configured a set of shared libs between your deployed
        application. And, of course, you don't want those shared libs on your wars.
      </para>

      <para>Based on real world scenarios, we made available a simple dependency management
        tool, that enables you explore and configure all the dependencies contained in
        the generated war file. This tool can be accessed just by clicking the "Manage Dependencies"
        button, and the following dialog will be displayed.
      </para>

      <figure>
        <title>Dependency Management Dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/NewServiceConfig9.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        This dialog presents the complete dependency tree of the service. To disable any
        particular dependency, all you need to do is "uncheck" it and press the "OK" button.
      </para>

      <para>
        Important to note that after configuring your dependencies you have to save the
        service configuration, in order to have the generated war file reflecting your
        configuration.
      </para>

    </section>

  </section>
</section>
