<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Working Sets</title>

  <para>Working Sets are a mean for grouping Facts and then defining
  constraints on them. You can create groups of Facts and only those Facts
  will be visible when authoring rules using the Guided Editor.</para>

  <para>Right now, Working Sets must be activated manually from the Guided
  Editor window (using the "Select Working Set" button placed in the toolbar).
  In the future, different Working Sets could be assigned to different users
  to reduce the scope and complexity when authoring rules.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Creating a new Working Set</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetCreation.png"
                   format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The figure above shows the window used to create or modify Working
    Sets. In this window you will find 2 lists. The list on the left side
    contains the possible Fact Types that can be added to the Working Set. These
    facts are those defined/imported in the package's model. The list on
    the
    right side contains the allowed Fact Types of this Working Set. When this
    Working Sets is active, only those Fact Types could be used while authoring
    rules using the Guided BRL Editor</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Defining Field Constraints inside a Working Set</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetConstraintCreation.png"
                   format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Once you have selected the valid Fact Types for a Working Set, you can
  add Constraints to the fields of those Facts Types. The image above shows
  how the Field Constraint tab looks like. In this configuration screen you
  will find:</para>

  <para>A.- Fact Types dropdown: Here you will find a list containing the
  Working Set's Fact Types</para>

  <para>B.- Field dropdown: Once you have selected a Fact Type, this dropdown
  will contain its fields.</para>

  <para>C.- Constraints List: This lists shows all the Constraints applied to
  the selected Field</para>

  <para>D.- Action Buttons: Using these buttons you will be able to add or
  remove Constraints to the selected Field. Right now, Guvnor provides a
  built-in collection of Constraints. The idea for next releases is to let
  users to plug their custom Constraints too.</para>

  <para>E.- Constraint's Attributes: In this section you will find all the
  attributes of the current Constraint that could be parametrized by the
  user.</para>

  <para>In the example above, a Matches Constraint is created for Car.brand
  field. This means that when rule authors use this field in a Rule condition,
  they should use a value valid according to this constraint, otherwise they
  will receive an error or warning.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Activating and Using Working Sets</title>

    <para>Working Sets are no active by default in Guvnor. Because this is an
    experimental feature, you must enable them manually in the Guided Editor
    panel if you want to use them. In the future, Working Sets will be
    associated to each user's profile.</para>

    <para>A new button was added in Guided Editor's Toolbar: "Select Working
    Sets". This button will open a popup with the list of the package's
    Working Sets. Using this popup you can activate one or more Working
    Sets.</para>

    <para>When Working Sets are activated, only the Fact Types allowed by them
    could be used when inserting new Patterns or Actions. The Patterns and
    Actions already present in the rule that contain prohibited Fact Types are
    marked as read only. Take a look at the next screen shots comparing the
    Guided Editor panel with and without Working Sets</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Comparison of "Add new Pattern" window using Working Set and
      without using them</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetFactConstraint.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In the image you can see how Working Sets could help rule's authors
    by reducing the amount of available Fact Types</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Comparison of "Add new Pattern" window using Working Set and
      without using them</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetFactConstraintRO.png"
                     format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Here you can see how Patterns containing prohibited Fact Types are
    switched to read only mode after Working Sets are activated.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using Field Constraint</title>

      <para>Up to now we have only cover how Facts are filtered using Working
      Sets. Another important feature of Working Sets is Field Constraints. We
      have already saw how to configure them, now we are going to explain how
      to use them.</para>

      <para>Because Field Constraints are defined inside a Working Set, we
      need to activate one or more Working Set to start working with them.
      Once a Working Set defining Field's Constraints is active we have two
      ways to use them: on demand validation and real-time validation.</para>

      <para>On demand validation is performed when you press the "Verify"
      button present in Guided Editor's toolbar. This button will fire a rule
      verification and will end up showing a report with the results. Any
      violated constraint will be shown as an error or warning according to
      its relevance</para>

      <figure>
        <title>On demand Field Constraints validation</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetFieldConstraintReport.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The image above shows the report that appears when a Working Set
      defines a Range Constraint on Driver.age. The age should be between 18
      and 80.</para>

      <para>Real-Time validation is an experimental feature (yes, inside
      another experimental feature like Working Sets) that checks for Field's
      Constraints violations in real time and mark the lines where the
      violations are using error or warning icons. This feature is disabled by
      default because sometimes it could be expensive. If you want to try it
      out, you should enable it in Administration -&gt; Rules Verification.
      This configuration is not yet persisted, so you need to enable it every
      time you start Guvnor.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Real-Time Field Constraints validation</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Guvnor/WorkingSetFieldConstraintRealTimeValidation.png"
                       format="PNG" xml:base="../../"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This Image shows the result of real-time validation. There you can
      see the same result as on demand validation, but you don't need to click
      any button, and the errors/warnings are shown in a more fashionable
      way!</para>

      <warning>
        <para>The problem with real-time validation is that right now only
        support "top level" Patterns.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
