<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>The business user perspective</title>

  <para>You can see from this manual, that some expertise and practice is
  required to use Guvnor. In fact any software system in some sense requires
  that people be "technical" even if it has a nice looking GUI. Having said
  that, in the right hands Guvnor can be setup to provide a suitable
  environment for non technical users.</para>

  <para>The most appropriate rule formats for this use are using the Guided
  editor, Decision tables and DSL rules. You can use some DSL expressions also
  in the guided editor (so it provides "forms" for people to enter
  values).</para>

  <para>You can use categories to isolate rules and assets from non technical
  users. Only assets which have a category assigned will appear in the
  "categories" view.</para>

  <para>The initial setup of Guvnor will need to be done by a
  developer/technical person who will set the foundations for all the rules.
  They may also create "templates" which are rules which may be copied (they
  would typically live in a "dummy" package, and have a category of "template"
  - this can also help ease the way).</para>

  <para>Deployment should also not be done by non technical users (as
  mentioned previously this happens from the "Package" feature).</para>

  <section>
    <title>Creating a business user view</title>

    <para>In most cases not all users will want to see all the functionality
    described here. You could have a subset of users who you only want to let
    view or edit certain sets of rules, without getting confused by all the
    other stuff. In this case you can use fine grained authorization (see the
    Admin Guide on how to initialize this). By setting permissions on a per
    category basis, users that only have category permissions will see a
    limited subset of functionality, and only items that are tagged with those
    categories.</para>
  </section>
</section>
