<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="./" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>The Guvnor application is packaged as a <filename>.war</filename> file, which can be deployed to any application
  server (such as JBoss AS, ...) or servlet container (such as Tomcat, ...) out-of-the-box.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Installation step by step</title>

    <para>Installation is simple: download, deploy, start and surf.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you don't have an application server or servlet container, download and install one. For example, <link
        xlink:href="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/">download JBoss AS</link>. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Download the Guvnor distribution</emphasis> from <link
        xlink:href="http://www.jboss.org/drools/downloads">the download site</link>. In the download zip, there's 1 war file per app server
        version, for example <filename>guvnor-5.2.0-jboss-eap-5.1.war</filename> for JBoss EAP 5.1. Use the war file best
        suited for your app server. Essentially there's little difference between those war files: mostly it's a matter
        of excluded jars which are already available on the app server.</para>

        <para>If no war specifically for your app server exists yet, take the latest Tomcat war. It might require minor
        configuration tweaks. Consult our wiki for specific tips. The community has been able to make it run on various
        platforms. Patches (pull requests) to expand our war assemblies for another app server or version are
        welcome.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Optionally rename that war file to <filename>guvnor.war</filename> to have a nicer URL. For the rest of
        the manual we'll presume you've done this.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Optionally customize the configuration. First <emphasis>explode</emphasis> (unzip) the
        <filename>war</filename> file, and change any configuration and then <emphasis>unexplode</emphasis> (zip) it
        again.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Deploy the war file</emphasis> by copying it into the deployment directory of the
        app server. For JBoss AS 5 and 6, that directory is <filename>server/default/deploy</filename>. Alternatively
        you can first explode (unzip) the war file and copy that exploded directory. Note: in JBoss AS, the exploded
        directory name must end with the suffix <filename>.war</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Start the app server</emphasis>. For JBoss AS 5 and 6, run
        <filename>$JBOSS_AS_HOME/bin/run.sh</filename> (or <filename>run.bat</filename>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Surf to the Guvnor webapp</emphasis>. This will probably be at
        <literal>localhost</literal> on port <literal>8080</literal>, for example at <link
        xlink:href="&guvnor.url.base;">&guvnor.url.base;</link> (the url
        depends on the name of the war file you're using).</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Supported and recommended platforms</title>

    <para>Guvnor runs in any application server or servlet container that supports Java SE 5 (JEE 5 is not required),
    this includes JBoss AS, Tomcat, Jetty and many more.</para>

    <para>JBoss AS is the recommended application server, because it is actively tested/developed on it. If you're
    looking for mission critical, enterprise support, <link
    xlink:href="http://www.jboss.com/products/platforms/brms/">take a look BRMS subscription</link>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
